Register of the World War I subject collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Recruiting, Registration, and Enlistment in the United States, Printed Matter, 1905-1920 (Boxes 20-21)
  - Typescript, "Some of the Advantages of an Enlistment in the Army,", circa 1919 (Box-folder 21: 29)
    Also includes a question-and-answer section with questions asked by men applying at Recruiting Stations.
  - Typescript, Western Union telegrams, 1919 (Box-folder 21: 30)
    Typed copies of telegrams sent to an Army Recruiting Officer in San Francisco, California, authorizing recruitment of applicants for Infantry, Coast Artillery, Engineers, Signal Corps, and Medical Department in the Panama, Hawaiian and Philippine departments (10 April 1919); acceptance of qualified applicants for the Quartermaster Corps in the Philippine Department (11 April 1919); and a deadline for enlistment for service in the American Expeditionary Forces, France (25 June 1919).
- Advertisements, miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 21: 31)
- Announcement cards, miscellaneous, 1917, 1919 (Box-folder 21: 32)
  Includes announcements about: a price increase at a restaurant; the mailing address for the United States Army, Western Department, San Francisco; an attorney resuming his practice; and safety suggestions for Moore Shipbuilding Company.
- Booklet, "Army Song Book, U.S.,", 1918 (Box-folder 21: 33)
  "For free distribution to all Officers and Men in the Army." Issued by the War Department Commission on Training Camp Activities and compiled with the assistance of the National Committee on Army and Navy Camp Music.
- Booklet, "Company B, 29th Engineers, American Expeditionary Forces,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 21: 34)
  Contains a brief statement about Company B, a roster of the company and the 447th Depot Detachment Engineers, which was attached to Company B, and copies of orders on which the company traveled from Camp Devens to Langres.
- Booklet, "Company 'I,' 3rd Battalion, 29th Engineers, 1918-1919,", circa 1919 (Box-folder 21: 35)
  Contains a history and roster of the company.
- Booklet, "Defense Against Gas,", 1919 (Box-folder 21: 36)
  Official A.E.F. No. 1433, G-5.
- Booklet, "Ephemeris of the Sun and Stars for the Year 1919,", 1918 (Box-folder 21: 37)
  General Headquarters, American Expeditionary Forces. Compiled by Lt. Col. C.H. Birdseye, C.A.C.
- Booklet, "How to be a Soldier: A compendium of useless information,", 1917 (Box-folder 21: 38)
- Booklet, "Infantry Regulations (Provisional), American Expeditionary Forces. Part 1,", 1918 (Box-folder 21: 39)
- Booklet, "Instructions on the Defensive Action of Large Units in Battle,", 1918 November (Box-folder 21: 40)
  A.E.F. No. 265, G-5. Translated from the French Edition of December 20, 1917, at General Headquarters, American Expeditionary Forces, France, March, 1918. Reprinted November, 1918.
- Booklet, "Methods for the Computation of Triangulation on the Grid System,", 1919 (Box-folder 22: 1)
  "A resume of lectures by Captain P. Ardon of the French Mission and 1st Lieut. Earl Church, 29th Engineers, U.S. Army, supplemented by results of studies and investigations by the Department of Computation and Triangulation, 1st Battalion, 29th Engineers."
- Booklet, "Notes on Branch Intelligence,", 1919 (Box-folder 22: 2)
  Issued by Second Section, General Staff, American Expeditionary Forces, 1 November 1918.
- Certificate, National Guard of California honorable discharge, 1915 December 3 (Box-folder 22: 3)
  For Eugene G. Lettermida(?).
- Correspondence, Boy Scouts of America, 1919 May (Box-folder 22: 4)
  Letters and leaflet about Boy Scout Week, 8-14 June 1919.
- Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 22: 5)
  Consists of letters and postcards, including "An acknowledgment of thanks from a Soldier at the Front."
- Correspondence, National Freight Bureau, 1920 April (Box-folder 22: 6)
  Form letter offering the Bureau's services for auditing freight bills and recovering overcharges.
- Drawing, Cylindrical Percussion Hand Grenade "Wilhelm," Figure 6, undated (Box-folder 22: 7)
- Drawing, Rifle Grenade, Model 1913, Figure 13, undated (Box-folder 22: 8)
- Drawing, Rifle Grenade, Model 1917, Figure 15, undated (Box-folder 22: 9)
- Forms, miscellaneous, 1917, 1921, undated (Box-folder 22: 10)
  Includes: blank copy of Service Record Form No. 29 A.G.O. (1917); blank copy of Individual Clothing Slip Q.M.C. Form No. 165, to be used by a soldier or organization commander and submitted to the quartermaster to request various items of clothing; blank copy of Mileage Voucher War Department Form No. 337; blank copy of Pay Allotment Q.M.C. Form 38, to be used by a soldier to allot a portion of his monthly pay to an individual; copy of Circular Proposal Inviting Bids Q.M.C. Form No. 119 (1921), for the S.F. General Intermediate Depot, Quartermaster Section, Fort Mason, San Francisco, CA, request for bids for miscellaneous supplies.
- Image, joint resolution of Congress declaring war on Germany, 1917 April 6 (Box-folder 22: 11)
  Photostat copy of the resolution, which was signed by Champ Clark (the Speaker of the House of Representatives), Thomas R. Marshall (the Vice President of the United States and President of the Senate), and Woodrow Wilson (the President of the United States).
- Labels, food wrappers, undated (Box-folder 22: 12)
  One label is from candy "manufactured from sugar allotted to us by the citizens of the State of Arkansas," and the other is from hard bread made by the National Biscuit Company for the U.S. Army.
- Leaflet, "America's Greatest Ace: Captain Eddie Rickenbacker, author of 'Fighting the Flying Circus,'", 1919 (Box-folder 22: 13)
  This leaflet provides some background information about Rickenbacker and his book.
- Leaflets, European aid, 1918, 1920 (Box-folder 22: 14)
  Includes leaflets published by the Serbian Relief Society of California, Jugoslav Relief (based in Chicago, Illinois), the California Committee for Relief in Serbia and France, and the National Allied Relief Committee.
- Leaflet, "An Experienced Friend Abroad,", 1917 (Box-folder 22: 15)
  Leaflet addressed to soldiers detailing the services American Express can provide for them while they are in Europe.
- Leaflet, "Extracts from Letters from France,", circa 1918 (Box-folder 22: 16)
  Published by the United States Forest Service for California, this leaflet includes portions of letters from: the American Expeditionary Forces, Division of Construction and Forestry; Arthur N. Davis' account of "The Kaiser as I knew Him for Fourteen Years," from the 10 August 1918 San Francisco Chronicle; Co. F, 10th Engineers, A.E.F.; a lumberman with the "Lumberjack" regiment; Lieutenant Gimbal, published in the 30 November 1918 Sacramento Bee, discussing forestry and timber in the war.
- Leaflets, House of Representatives bills, 1919 December 12 (Box-folder 22: 17)
  Text of bills introduced in the House of Representatives, 66th Congress, Second Session. Includes H.R. 11117, "A bill defining sedition, the promoting thereof, providing punishment therefor, and for other purposes;" H.R. 11205, "A bill providing for the exclusion, deportation, and expulsion from the United States of certain aliens, and for other purposes;" and H.R. 11231, "A bill defining criminal syndicalism and sabotage, proscribing certain acts and methods in connection therewith and in pursuance thereof, and providing penalties and punishments therefor." All three bills were introduced by Mr. John E. Raker, a representative from California.
- Leaflet, "Jews in the Czecho-Slovak State,", 1919 January (Box-folder 22: 18)
  Published by the Bohemian (Czech) National Alliance of America in response to an editorial about Jews in Bohemia that appeared in the Chicago Evening American on 28 December 1918.
- Leaflet, "Keeping Fit,", 1918 October (Box-folder 22: 19)
  Pamphlet No. 12, issued by the Bureau of Social Hygiene, California State Board of Health in cooperation with the Department of the Department of the Interior, Bureau of Education.
- Leaflet, "Patriotism,", 1915 May 28 (Box-folder 22: 20)
  Bulletin No. 81, published by the International Information Bureau.
- Leaflet, "Popular Government and Universal Training,", circa 1919 (Box-folder 22: 21)
- Leaflet, "Printers' Ink,", circa 1920 (Box-folder 22: 22)
  Published by the American Press Association, this particular issue discusses country newspapers and advertising therein.
- Leaflet, Seventy-Five table lamp, circa 1919 (Box-folder 22: 23)
  Advertising description of the shade designed by Franklin Booth for a Seventy-Five table lamp, made by Snead and Company from artillery shells that survived an explosion at a Morgan, N.J. armaments plant. In addition to lauding the artistic nature of the lamp shade, it also states that Booth drew inspiration from "Grass," by John J. Ingalls (a former senator from Kansas), and this is printed on the reverse side.
- Leaflet, "A Study of the Cost of Living,", 1919 April 19 (Box-folder 22: 24)
  By Katherine Philips Edison, Executive Officer, Industrial Welfare Commission, State of California.
- Leaflet, "U.S. Immigration Service Bulletin,", 1919 March 1 (Box-folder 22: 25)
  Includes sections on "Amendments to Chinese Rules," "Proposed Immigration Legislation," and "Immigration Statistics for January, 1919."
- Leaflet, "Victory Medal Circular,", 1920 May 20 (Box-folder 22: 26)
  Circular No. 188, published by the War Department, covering "Issue of Victory Medal, battle clasps, and clasps, for service in the World War."
- Leaflet, "Virginia Health Bulletin,", 1919 September (Box-folder 22: 27)
  Volume XI, No. 6, about the flu and how to prevent it.
- List, "'Honor List' of Unofficial War Photographs,", 1919 April 10 (Box-folder 22: 28)
  Photographs "selected on the basis of historical significance, human interest and artistic merit by Major Kendall Banning, Pictorial Section, Historical Branch, War Plans Division, General Staff." Only the list, not the photographs themselves, is included, though the list contains a description of the photographs.
- List, "Vote in Congress on the Final Passage of the Joint Resolution Declaring War on Germany,", circa 1917 (Box-folder 22: 29)
  Two lists (one for the Senate, one for the House of Representatives), indicating by last name the Yeas, Nays, and Abstainments for the vote.
- Lyrics and poetry/creative writing, miscellaneous, 1915, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 22: 30)
- Membership applications and subscriptions, miscellaneous, 1916-1919, undated (Box-folder 22: 31)
- Menu, Thanksgiving, Company I, 29th Engineers, 1918 November 28 (Box-folder 22: 32)
  As well as a menu for the Thanksgiving meal, the reverse side of the card features a roster of G-2-C-First U.S. Army, with the names and hometowns of the members of the company.
- Newspaper clippings, The New York Times, "President Wilson's Speech in Baltimore,", 1918 April 7 (Box-folder 22: 33)
- Postcards, "Scraps of Paper. German Proclamations: Bills Posted in Belgium and France,", circa 1916 (Box-folder 22: 34)
  Text on postcards is in English and in French. See also: Booklet in Box 18, Folder 12.
- Press release, Federal Trade Commission - packer legislation, 1919 August (Box-folder 22: 35)
  Article written by Hugh McIsaac, Washington newspaperman, about pending legislation to regulate the packers and the arguments for and against it.
- Press releases, miscellaneous, circa 1919-1920 (Box-folder 22: 36)
  Also includes some correspondence sent to newspaper editors.
- Printed matter, Army and Navy insignia, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 22: 37)
  Included in this folder are two undated newspaper clippings about Navy insignia ("Naval Officers' Sleeve Ranking Devices" and "What U.S. Navy Officers' Shoulder Marks Mean"), a 1917 booklet titled "Army and Navy Insignia," and a 1918 monthly tear-away calendar mounted on an illustrated sheet titled "Insignia of the United States Army and Navy."
- Printed matter, British recruiting in North America, circa 1917 (Box-folder 22: 38)
  Includes forms and applications, as well as flyers urging British men in North America to enlist.
- Printed matter, Central Officers Training School, 1918 (Box-folder 22: 39)
  Includes a memorandum of information, correspondence, and a blank application for admission.
- Printed matter, examination for commission as Provisional Second Lieutenant, Corps of Engineers, Regular Army, 1917 (Box-folder 22: 40)
  Includes a memo regarding the examination and its requirements; a letter responding to a request for information about the examination, which provides the date of the examination and what subjects will be covered; and a form to be filled out by an applicant for the appointment.
- Printed matter, France, circa 1918 (Box-folder 22: 41)
  Includes a drawing (clipped from a newspaper), booklets, leaflets, a hotel bill, ticket stubs, forms, and stationery.
- Printed matter, hospitals, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 22: 42)
  This folder consists of items relating to U.S. Army Field Hospital #13 in Einville, France and a German prisoner of war who was treated there; as well as items relating to base hospitals in France and the treatment of a Lieutenant Ernest Gorman.
- Printed matter, investing, 1917-1920 (Box-folder 22: 43)
  Includes correspondence from banks and a corporation about investment opportunities (bonds, foreign exchange).
- Printed matter, readjustment and placement of returning soldiers, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 22: 44)
  Includes leaflets, correspondence, rosters, and press releases.
- Printed matter, Swift & Company, 1918, 1920 (Box-folder 22: 45)
  Includes a newspaper clipping from The Chicago Tribune, 27 February 1918, "Swift Replies to Heney: Packer Says Attorney Seeks Political Glory; Calls Packers Patriotic;" and a financial statement for the year ended 1 November 1919, as submitted to the 35th Annual Meeting of Shareholders, 8 January 1920.
- Printed matter, troop transport, 1917-1918, 1921 (Box-folder 23: 1)
  Includes a newspaper clipping about President Wilson's 4 December 1918 trip to France aboard the steamship George Washington; instructions for troops aboard the U.S.S. Northern Pacific; blank issue slips for U.S. Army Transport; materials from the U.S.S. America, including a holiday card, a Christmas booklet, and blank stationery; an issue of The Sapper, published on a U.S. transport; issues of the U.S. Navy Press from May 1918; and a 3 February 1921 circular advertisement from the Transportation Service for the sale of floating equipment.
- Printed matter, United Kingdom, circa 1918 (Box-folder 23: 2)
  Includes a booklet, a hotel bill and notice, and ticket stubs.
- Printed matter, Visalia Stock Saddle Company, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 23: 3)
  Includes correspondence related to the war effort and providing equipment; a proposal for supplies or services; inquiries for quotations from the Office of the Director of Purchase, United States Army, Clothing and Equipment; and Bureau of the Census materials relating to the production of leather goods. With the inquiries for quotations are two drawings related to the requested items: McClellan saddle, model of 1904; and cavalry bridle, model of 1909, curb and snaffle-bits, model of 1909, and curb chain, model of 1912.
- Programs and invitations/tickets, miscellaneous, circa 1918-1919 (Box-folder 23: 4)
- Receipts and packing slips, miscellaneous, circa 1918-1919 (Box-folder 23: 5)
- Report, American Commission to Negotiate Peace, 1919 August 22 (Box-folder 23: 6)
  S.H. Bulletin No. 756: Report by the British Admiralty on the scuttling of the German Fleet at Scapa Flow, 27 June 1919.
- Reports, Second Army Radio Press, 1919 (Box-folder 23: 7)
  Issued daily by Radio Office, 2nd Army, 1st Lt. J.A. Zimmermann, Radio Officer. The bulletins are from France, on March 5th, 6th, 9th, and 11th and April 3rd, 1919.
- Reports, "Summary of Intelligence,", 1918-1919 (Box-folder 23: 8)
  From the 32nd Division, A.E.F., Second Section, G.S., Series "F," Nos. 39 - 44. Includes sections on "General Impression of the Day," "Enemy Order of Battle," "Enemy Movements," "Enemy Morale," "Political Situation," "Economic Situation," "Observation of the Armistice," "Population of the Newly Occupied Territory," "Released Prisoners of War," and "Miscellaneous." It would appear that this Division was stationed somewhere in Germany.
- Stationery, miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 23: 9)
  Includes blank postcards and stationery.
- Typescript, "The Masonic Club and Its Activities During the World War,", 1919 April (Box-folder 23: 10)
  Narrative of the experiences of the San Francisco, California Masonic Club.
- Typescripts, miscellaneous, 1913, undated (Box-folder 23: 11)
  Includes "Job Order" and "Weekly Report of Repairs" forms for the U.S.S. Justin; United States Government Insurance Information Bulletin No. 1, Revised; Notice of Goods for Sale (food items; according to a handwritten note the list was posted in a Nevada City post office); page of a report on inductions in Amador County, California; a page from a report on the 4th Division's war experience; and two pages that seem to relate to a visit by President Wilson (consisting of a list of individuals present, as well as an annotated list of automobile assignments).
- Typescripts, Waban Gazette, 1919 November (Box-folder 23: 12)
  According to a handwritten note, this was published on board the S.S. Waban (a former United States Navy steamer that became a mercantile ship) as it was crossing the Pacific. Some pages are missing.
- Miscellany, circa 1918-1920 (Box-folder 23: 13)
  Includes a special pass from Air Service Flying School in San Diego, California; print of a drawing of the Kaiser in a chess match; ephemera related to savings and conservation during the war; and envelopes.
- United States Organizations and Agencies, Printed Matter, 1909, 1917-1923 (Boxes 23-25)
  This series largely consists of printed matter produced by organizations and government agencies during World War I and the immediate years afterward. The materials document the activities of these organizations during this time period, both in general and as they relate to the war.
  - American Commission on Irish Independence, et al., 1918-1921 (Box-folder 23: 14)
    Includes materials from the American Commission on Irish Independence, the American Committee for Relief in Ireland, the Friends of Irish Freedom, and the Women's Irish League in support of the Irish Republic, such as leaflets, flyers, and press releases.
  - American Committee for Relief in the Near East, 1918-1923 (Box-folder 23: 15-16)
    Formerly known as the American Committee for Armenian and Syrian Relief. Includes leaflets, press releases, correspondence, posters and articles about the plight of Armenian refugees and the work of the American Committee for Relief in the Near East.
  - American Expeditionary Forces, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 24: 1)
    Includes orders, leave passes, and postcards (one handwritten, the rest blank).
  - American Legion, 1919 (Box-folder 24: 2)
    This folder contains pamphlets, registration cards, event tickets and invitations related to the American Legion, particularly posts in the San Francisco Bay Area.
  - American Red Cross, 1918 (Box-folder 24: 3)
    Includes a leaflet, "How to Secure an Audience: A Pamphlet of Suggestions;" an Annual Report by the Secretary of the San Francisco Chapter of the American National Red Cross, 14 October 1918; blank stationery; a wrapper for an "NRG" Bar distributed by the Red Cross to those in the Service; blank Red Cross Christmas Roll Call forms; and a paper Red Cross Service Flag to be displayed in the front window of the home.
  - Committee on Public Information, circa 1917-1918 (Box-folder 24: 4)
    Includes correspondence regarding the purchase of the Committee's publications, including the "Daily Official Bulletin," as well as a copy of the "Weekly War News Digest" for March and June 1918.
  - Internal Revenue Service, 1917-1920 (Box-folder 24: 5)
    Includes press releases, leaflets, blank income tax forms (1040A), and correspondence providing information and instructions about new tax laws. Items are published by the Internal Revenue Service and by related industries (such as banks or vendors offering their services with completing tax forms).
  - Knights of Columbus, circa 1918 - 1920 (Box-folder 24: 6)
    Includes blank postcards featuring scenes from Knights of Columbus buildings in Europe; the Manual of the National Catholic War Council; a piece of correspondence; a leaflet and a card welcoming servicemen to the Knights of Columbus camp; blank stationery; and a flyer advertising the publication of Knights of Columbus in Peace and War.
  - Liberty Loans, 1918-1920 (Box-folder 24: 7)
    Includes materials relating to the Third, Fourth and Victory Liberty Loans: leaflets, posters, blank subscription/application forms, and correspondence (mainly form letters requesting support).
  - Pacific Telephone and Telegraph Company, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 24: 8)
    Leaflets from Pacific Telephone and Telegraph Company regarding new toll and exchange rates, as well as an appeal to use the telephone less during the influenza epidemic, due to a shortage of operators.
  - United States Department of Agriculture, 1918-1920 (Box-folder 24: 9)
    Includes flyers, newsletters and press releases about the work of the Department of Agriculture and information and materials for individuals related to food and farming.
  - United States Department of the Interior, 1909, 1917, 1919 (Box-folder 24: 10)
    Includes Bureau of Mines materials (a certificate of Mine Rescue Training, as well as photos of men wearing a Proto breathing apparatus) and a 6 May 1919 letter enclosing an outline of each state's actions regarding soldier-settlement bills. The remainder of the materials relate to the Act of Congress titled "An Act to Provide Relief in Cases of Contracts Connected with the Prosecution of the War and for Other Purposes," approved 2 March 1919, and include a summary of the regulations regarding settlement for those producing manganese, chrome, pyrites, or tungsten, and a questionnaire to be filled out by those seeking settlement for the same.
  - United States Department of Labor, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 24: 11)
    Includes correspondence sent to newspaper editors asking them to endorse Department of Labor movements; blank application forms for farm work employment and farm help; and leaflets about the labor outlook and prices.
  - United States Food Administration, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 25: 1)
    Includes publications by the United States Food Administration covering general and special license regulations, a narrative about the work of the Food Administration in Amador County, California, and War Cook Book for American Women: Suggestions for Patriotic Service in the Home (compiled by Frederic J. Haskin with an introductory letter from President Woodrow Wilson to Herbert Hoover).
  - United States Railroad Administration, 1917-1919 (Box-folder 25: 2)
    Includes passenger check tickets; timetables; furlough fare certificate; dining car menus; leaflets distributed to employees, the public, and the government about the railroad service under Federal control; and press releases about the freight car situation.
  - War Savings Service and War Savings Stamps, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 25: 3)
    Includes stamps, applications/pledge forms (both blank and completed), leaflets, and correspondence (mainly form letters requesting support).
  - Y.M.C.A., circa 1918-1920 (Box-folder 25: 4)
    Consists of press releases (including four from the Y.W.C.A.); leaflets providing facts about the work of the Y.M.C.A. in Europe and disputing charges against it; a program from the Trianon Theatre in France; and blank stationery.